Okay, next section is autoimmune disorders. These are characterized by immune mediated damage of
self-tissues. The idea here is that the immune system begins to react against the self-antigen
and as it reacts against the self-antigen, there is damage to tissues. If we wanted to be a little
more precise, we could say primary immune mediated damage because if you think about it,
the immune system does damage tissues, for example, with infection. So let's say the patient gets a
viral infection and the immune system begins to destroy the virally infected cells. In that
particular case, we are damaging self-tissue, but the target is the virus. It's not the self-tissue,
whereas in this particular case, the target is a self-antigen that then results in the damage.
So that's kind of a subtle distinction. There's about a 1 to 2 percent prevalence of these disorders
in the United States, and so all of us are going to see this in our clinical practice.
The underlying premise of autoimmunity is that there is a loss of self-tolerance. To understand
this, let's go back to normal. So we have B-cells and we have T-cells, and of course the B-cells,
they recognize antigen via immunoglobulin, and the T-cells, they recognize antigen via the T-cell
receptor. Now, we produce a broad spectrum of T-cell receptors and immunoglobulin because we have to deal
with a broad spectrum of antigens that could come in from the outside world. And so we generate this
broad spectrum, but remember that the generation of immunoglobulin and T-cell receptor is random.
And so while we generate T-cell receptor and immunoglobulin, we also generate some T-cell receptor
and immunoglobulin that is reactive against self-antigens. And so that's why I stay here,
that self-reactive lymphocytes are regularly generated. Now, in order to deal with these self-reactive
lymphocytes, we have a process called tolerance, which helps to sort of take care of them, and we'll
talk about this in more detail moving forward. Tolerance can occur centrally, which means that it
occurs in the generative organs. It occurs in the organs in which the lymphocytes develop, or it can
occur peripherally, which means it occurs outside of the areas where the lymphocytes develop, instead in
the peripheral tissues. So let's start with central tolerance. Central tolerance will occur in two
places. It'll occur where the T-cells develop, which is the thymus, and it'll also occur where the B-cells
develop, which is going to be the bone marrow. So we're going to focus on the thymus, and then we'll
move to the bone marrow in a moment. Let's go back and review what happens in the thymus as the T-cells
develop. So the stem cells that are eventually to become T-cells come from the bone marrow, through
the blood, and eventually enter into the thymus. When they enter into the thymus, they undergo varying
stages of development, so that they eventually become double positive cells, and double positive
basically means that they express CD4 and CD8, that's why they're double positive, and they
also express T-cell receptor. Once they express T-cell receptor, they then eventually will progress
to become single positive, which means that they'll either express CD4 or CD8, and eventually,
exit as naive mature T-cells. So these naive mature T-cells would go out into the periphery.
Now, as the cells are developing, they undergo various checkpoints that allow them to move to
the next step. So for example, the double positive cells undergo something here, which is called
positive selection. Positive selection means that the double positive cells are checked to
see whether they can bind MHC and antigen, meaning do they bind antigen when it's bound to MHC?
So they have to be able to recognize MHC. If the double positive cells are able to recognize MHC,
they can progress to become single positive cells. If they can't, they undergo apoptosis and they die.
So that's called positive selection. It selects cells that are MHC-restricted, and that's how we
get MHC restriction within our T-cells. The single positive cells eventually undergo a checkpoint,
and that is called negative selection. And in negative selection, what happens is the question is asked,
do the single positive cells bind self-antigen? If they avidly bind self-antigen, then they undergo apoptosis,
and if they don't, then they're allowed to progress and exit from the thymus. Now, if you think about this,
negative selection is very important because by asking the question, do you bind self-antigen,
and then killing off those cells, we're actually removing self-reactive lymphocytes.
Remember, the T-cell receptor was generated randomly. It could be specific for self-antigen.
If it binds self-antigen within the thymus, then those cells will die via negative selection,
and we won't have to send them into the periphery so that they could theoretically attack self-tissues.
So negative selection is essential for the removal of self-reactive lymphocytes.
This is a little bit of a background concerning central tolerance, and I've mentioned that here in your text,
where I see that central tolerance occurs in the thymus, and of course that's going to be for the T-cells.
Now, just to highlight the importance of central tolerance, I've mentioned a very rare disorder,
which is called autoimmune polyendocrine syndrome, that can arise when central tolerance goes awry.
Remember the developmental sort of drawing that I had given you?
There's a stem cell which enters into the thymus, and then eventually becomes a double positive thymocyte
with CD4, CD8, and T-cell receptor, which then eventually becomes a single positive thymocyte,
which basically means that it's CD4 positive or CD8 positive, and eventually that will exit as a naive mature T-cell.
So this is the normal that we've already mentioned.
Now at this point, as the single positive cell is heading towards the exit of the thymus,
it will undergo a process called negative selection.
And negative selection, it's important to know, that negative selection actually occurs here in the medulla of the thymus,
this being the cortex.
Now, in order for negative selection to occur, these thymocytes must be exposed to antigen
that would normally be present in the periphery, in the body.
So for example, there are dendritic cells present within this medulla that express a wide array of self-antigen on MHC,
so that the cells can be tested to see whether they bind self-antigen.
And there is also a cell called the medullary epithelial cell that also expresses a wide array of peripheral antigens on MHC.
These can also be shown to the lymphocyte in order to see whether it binds those self-antigens.
Now, of course, if the lymphocyte binds the self-antigens either on the dendritic cell or on the medullary epithelial cell,
then the, and by the way, this is a medullary epithelial cell,
then if it binds these self-antigens, then the cell will undergo apoptosis and will die.
And that's how we'll get rid of self-reactive lymphocytes.
Now, the medullary epithelial cell, in order to express some of these self-antigens,
has a transcription factor in the nucleus, which is called air.
Air is necessary for expression of some of these self-antigens.
Now, imagine, if we don't have air, we won't be able to express some subset of self-antigens.
If we can't express some subset of self-antigens, then lymphocytes that are generated against that subset
will be able to escape out into the periphery and will have self-reactive lymphocytes within the periphery.
And that's what happens in this disorder called autoimmune polyendocrine syndrome.
Patients have air mutations, and so, therefore, lymphocytes that are reactive to antigens that are dependent upon air
will be able to escape, and in particular, these patients develop autoimmunity that destroys endocrine glands.
In fact, there's a triad that's seen in this disorder.
The first is that the patients get hypoparathyroidism.
The second is that the patients get adrenal failure.
And the third problem that these patients get is that they get chronic candida infections of the skin and the oral mucosa.
So, this is the triad, and so you can see here that it's due to the autoimmunity that you get destruction of the parathyroids
and destruction of the adrenals that then results in this disorder.
Now, moving on to the bone marrow, central tolerance also occurs in the bone marrow, and, of course, that's going to be for the B cells.
Now, when you think about the B cells, it's kind of very similar.
Here we are in the bone marrow. The stem cell is actually generated in the bone marrow.
So, it simply is in the bone marrow, and then it progresses, and it becomes an immature B cell.
And then, it progresses from there to eventually exit the bone marrow as a naive, mature B cell.
So, that's sort of the very simplistic normal development that occurs within the bone marrow.
Now, as the cell progresses from a stem cell to an immature B cell, it's going to express immunoglobulin.
And then, the question is going to be asked, somewhere out here, via negative selection, do you bind self-antigen too tightly?
So, there are dendritic cells that are present within the bone marrow that express self-antigen.
And, as they express self-antigen, the immunoglobulin will be exposed to it, and if it binds too tightly, then the cells will undergo one of two things.
Now, the first thing that can happen as a result of negative selection is that the B cells can undergo receptor editing.
So, what happens in receptor editing is that the RAG genes that are essential for the development of the immunoglobulin specificities will be re-expressed.
So, as you get re-expression of the RAG genes, which will then allow for editing of the light chain of the immunoglobulin.
And, once the light chain gets edited, the hope is that it will no longer bind self-antigen, and so that would allow the B cell to remain functional and go out into the periphery.
So, one possibility that can occur through negative selection is receptor editing via re-expression of RAG genes.
Another possibility is that if you can't edit the receptor, is that you simply undergo apoptosis.
So, cells here can also undergo apoptosis, and that would be through the mitochondrial pathway.
So, anyway, this again is highlighting the importance of tolerance and the way by which we protect ourselves against self-reactive lymphocytes.
Now, let's assume for a moment that the central tolerance mechanisms fail, or that some rare cells are able to escape central tolerance.
Well, we have a second line of defense, and that is called peripheral tolerance.
And, what happens in peripheral tolerance is that if an antigen is recognized in the peripheral tissues without a co-stimulation, without a co-stimulatory signal,
then the lymphocyte will undergo energy, which means it will shut down, or it will undergo apoptosis.
So, just to highlight this, let's just imagine for a moment that you have a CD4-positive T cell,
and the CD4-positive T cell is using its T cell receptor in order to bind antigen being presented by this dendritic cell.
So, here is your MHC2 with the associated antigen, and you've got this sort of first interaction occurring.
Now, when this first interaction occurs, it also requires a second interaction in order to activate the T cell.
So, for example, in this particular instance, the second interaction would be that CD28, on the T cell,
would bind a molecule called B7 being expressed by the dendritic cell.
This would provide the second signal, and it's when the second signal arises that the CD4-positive T cell would actually become activated.
Now, let's imagine that there's a self-reactive CD4-positive T cell that's floating around.
It goes into the periphery, and it binds, using its T cell receptor, it binds some peripheral antigen.
Now, when it does that, you would expect that there would be no second signal,
because there's no inflammation or anything generating a second signal.
And so, if there's no second signal, then this CD4-positive T cell will undergo energy.
And energy, of course, just means that the cell basically shuts down and goes to sleep.
So, that's one possibility.
Now, another possibility is that this CD4-positive T cell regularly and consistently keeps binding antigen.
It repeatedly binds antigen without this secondary, without this co-stimulatory second signal.
And in that particular case, then the other possibility would be that this CD4-positive T cell will undergo apoptosis.
And the apoptosis occurs in a very interesting way.
The CD4-positive T cell has a receptor present on the cell, which is called CD95.
It's also known as FAS, and this is a death receptor.
If you have regular binding of the T cell receptor to antigen without the regular and consistent binding,
without the second signal, then the CD4-positive T cell will eventually begin to express FAS ligand.
And when it expresses FAS ligand, FAS ligand will bind the FAS receptor, which is CD95,
and that is a death receptor, which will then indicate to the cell that it needs to undergo apoptosis.
At the same time, this FAS ligand, let's say that there's another B cell or T cell nearby.
This would be another T cell or another B cell.
If this FAS ligand were to bind CD95 on another T cell or CD95 on another B cell,
it would also induce apoptosis of other B and T cells that might be self-reactive as well.
So, essentially, there's two ways by which peripheral tolerance occurs.
Number one, through energy, and number two, through apoptosis.
In order to highlight the importance of peripheral tolerance, I want to mention a very rare syndrome again.
This is called autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome.
And, basically, what happens in autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome is that you have mutations in the FAS apoptosis pathway.
So, remember, let's go back. Let's say that this is that CD4 positive T cell.
So, of course, you need to have the receptor, which was CD95, also called FAS.
You need to be able to have the ligand, which was called FAS ligand.
And, you also need to be able to have the caspases that are necessary or that get activated through this pathway.
In particular, one caspase that's important is caspase 10.
So, imagine if a patient has a mutation such as they lose FAS, or, more rarely, if they have a mutation where they lose FAS ligand or CD10,
they would no longer be able to undergo this apoptotic pathway in the periphery.
And, therefore, that would allow for the survival of some self-reactive lymphocytes.
And so, in this particular disorder that we're discussing, there is mutations in the FAS apoptosis pathway.
Again, the more common mutation being in FAS itself, but it can also occur in FAS ligand or caspase 10.
And, that results in something called autoimmune lymphoproliferative syndrome.
Now, the autoimmune basically implies that the patients have cells that are self-reactive lymphocytes.
And, actually, what happens is that these cells generate immunoglobulin, in particular, IgG, against cells in the blood.
And so, these patients can get cytopenias. For example, they can get an anemia or a thrombocytopenia.
Where the lymphoproliferative part of the syndrome implies that they get proliferation of the lymphocytes,
because they can't get rid of these self-reactive lymphocytes.
And so, those self-reactive lymphocytes can actually proliferate and expand the lymphoid compartments.
And so, for example, areas where lymphocytes normally live will become enlarged.
For example, they get something called lymphadenopathy, or enlargement of the lymph nodes throughout the body.
It's a generalized lymphadenopathy.
They also get hepatosplenomegaly.
And, because there's so much proliferation of the lymphoid cells,
eventually mutations can be picked up and these patients can eventually get lymphoma.
Now, again, you're never going to see this disorder because it's extremely rare.
But, why it's important is because it highlights the essence of peripheral tolerance
and how important it is in getting rid of self-reactive lymphocytes.
And so, this is something to be aware of as well, especially because it ties into some basic immunology.
Now, we do have a third way by which we can protect ourselves against self-reactive lymphocytes.
And that is through a special subset of T cells called regulatory T cells.
Regulatory T cells are CD4 positive T cells that suppress immune responses.
They actually act in two ways.
The first way in which they act is that they can block T cell activation.
So, for example, let's say that this is the CD4 positive T cell.
And this is the dendritic cell that is presenting the antigen.
So, you've got your T cell receptor and you've got this MHC class II molecule that has antigen that the T cells responding against.
Now, let's imagine for a second that this is a T cell that is against a self-antigen.
So, it's a self-reactive lymphocyte.
Of course, it's going to need the second signal, CD28, which would bind B7.
But what can happen is that you can have a regulatory T cell come in.
So, this is a Treg.
And the regulatory T cells actually express a molecule called CTLA4.
CTLA4.
And CTLA4 can compete and can actually bind B7.
So, as CTLA4 competes and binds B7, that decreases the probability of a second signal.
And therefore, these T cells might, for example, undergo energy.
Another way by which the regulatory T cells can inhibit immune responses is by secreting cytokines.
So, two cytokines that they secrete are, number one, IL-10, and number two, TGF-beta.
IL-10 is important because it inhibits macrophages and dendritic cells.
In fact, in particular, it inhibits or limits the expression of MHC class II.
So, if you limit the expression of MHC class II, obviously, you don't have much for the T cell receptor to bind.
And similarly, IL-10 also limits the production of costumulatory molecules.
So, you would limit the production of B7, for example.
And that would also, again, decrease the interaction or the ability to activate these self-reactive T cells.
And then, of course, the second cytokine is TGF-beta, and TGF-beta also inhibits activation of macrophages.
So, this is a little bit of a summary of the way in which regulatory T cells work.
Now, when you think about regulatory T cells, there's kind of a phenotype that you should be aware of.
They are CD4 positive, CD25 positive, and FOXP3 positive.
CD4 indicates that they are CD4 positive T cells.
CD25 is also known as IL-2 receptor.
And this helps me to remember that the CD, that the regulatory T cells are dependent on IL-2 for growth and survival.
So, this is important.
Again, CD25 being part of the IL-2 receptor.
And then, finally, the FOXP3, FOXP3 is a transcription factor, and regulatory T cells are dependent on FOXP3 for both their development and their maintenance.
So, this is a little bit of the phenotype that you should be aware of concerning regulatory T cells.
Now, let's go back to the slide for a minute, because I want to show you the importance of regulatory T cells as far as human disease is concerned.
One of the things that we know is that CD25 polymorphisms are associated with autoimmunity.
For example, there's a relationship between multiple sclerosis and type 1 diabetes.
Now, one explanation of this could be that CD25 is essential for regulatory T cells.
Remember that there's CD4 positive, CD25 positive, and FOXP3 positive.
So, if we have polymorphisms of CD25, which is part of the IL-2 receptor, and IL-2 is essential for development and survival of regulatory T cells,
perhaps CD25 polymorphisms are affecting the regulatory T cell subset and, therefore, resulting in autoimmunity.
So, there is an association of CD25 polymorphisms with autoimmunity, for example, multiple sclerosis and type 1 diabetes.
Another important thing to recognize is that FOXP3 mutations result in autoimmunity, in particular, a very particular syndrome called IPEX syndrome.
The I stands for immune dysfunction, the P stands for polyendocrinopathy, the E stands for enteropathy, and the X stands for X-linked.
And so, what happens in these patients is that they get autoimmune dysfunction, which then results in endocrinopathy.
And the endocrinopathy can be thyroiditis, with inflammation and destruction of the thyroid gland, or type 1 diabetes, with inflammation and destruction of the islets and the pancreas.
And they also get autoimmune enteropathy, which then leads to diarrhea.
So, this is another example of the immune system damaging tissues, whether they be endocrine or whether they be in the gut.
And then finally, the X represents the fact that this is an X-linked syndrome.
These patients usually also have eczema of the skin, and it usually arises in an infant.
So, again, very rare syndromes, but highlight the importance of regulatory T cells in this discussion.
A few more very quick principles.
Autoimmune disorders tend to be more common in women.
They classically will affect women of childbearing age.
One theory here is that estrogen reduces the apoptosis of self-reactive B cells.
Remember that self-reactive B cells will undergo apoptosis, either in the bone marrow or in the periphery, when they bind self-antigen.
So, if you have estrogen and it blocks that apoptosis, that would increase the risk of autoimmunity.
And, of course, there's a lot of estrogen in women of childbearing age.
Another important principle concerning autoimmunity is that it's our current sort of understanding that this arises in a genetically susceptible individual who is exposed to an environmental trigger.
Now, as far as the genetic susceptibility is concerned, the reason why we believe that is because we know that there's an increased incidence in twins.
So, that implies that there's some sort of genetic component to these disorders.
When you study the genes that may be responsible, the strongest association is with HLA subtypes.
Now, HLA are the genes that code for MHC, and so it kind of makes sense because most autoimmune disorders are against protein,
and so you would think, or it would make sense, that the HLA subtypes would be important.
In particular, among the HLA subtypes, the strongest association among HLA subtypes is with HLAB27,
and its association with a disorder called ankylosing spondylitis.
Now, we're going to cover that later in the course, but I just want to highlight the strongest association with HLA subtypes is with that particular subtype, HLAB27,
with a disorder called ankylosing spondylitis.
When you look at non-HLA genes, then one of the strongest associations, or we can say perhaps one of the genes that's most frequently linked to autoimmunity,
is a gene called PTPN22, and so polymorphisms of PTPN22 are also associated with autoimmunity.
Now, PTPN22 is actually a tyrosine phosphatase, and when you, the mutations actually result in a, or the polymorphisms I should say, result in a gain of function,
which decreases the signaling necessary for tolerance.
And so, that's sort of one of the theories, is that in order to develop tolerance, you need to have signaling.
For example, the cell needs to bind self-antigen, and then a signal is sent telling the cell to undergo energy.
However, if the signaling mechanisms are awry, for example, with a PTPN22 polymorphism, then that would increase the risk of developing autoimmunity.
So, these are some genes that, that could be potentially associated with autoimmunity.
Now, at the same time, it's not enough to have genetic susceptibility, there also needs to be an environmental trigger.
To get a better handle on this, let's go back to the whiteboard.
So, you've got this patient who has a genetic susceptibility, and we assume that the genetic susceptibility is going to result in some sort of loss of self-tolerance.
And when there's a loss of tolerance, we assume that the patient is going to generate some sort of self-reactive lymphocyte.
Now, this self-reactive lymphocyte, one or two, for example, is not going to be able to generate autoimmunity.
In order to get autoimmunity, we're going to need expansion of the population of self-reactive lymphocytes, along with activation of the self-reactive lymphocytes.
And so, in order for that to occur, we also require, along with genetic susceptibility, we also require an environmental trigger.
Some examples of triggers, one would be that the patient simply gets an infection with, for example, some other virus or bacteria.
And when they get this infection, that revs up the immune system and activates the antigen-presenting cells.
And as a sort of side effect of the inflammation, or almost as a bystander, this self-reactive lymphocyte gets activated, and that then can result in autoimmunity.
So, that's called bystander activation, because the self-reactive lymphocyte gets activated sort of as a bystander.
Another possibility is this self-reactive lymphocyte gets exposed, or let's say that the patient gets exposed, to a bacteria that has a molecule that also happens to activate this self-reactive lymphocyte.
So, the bacteria has a molecule that's similar to a self-antigen.
So, when this bacteria comes in, it infects the patient, the self-reactive lymphocyte will get activated, and then will eventually be able to produce autoimmunity as well.
And this is called molecular mimicry, because the antigen on the microbe mimics or resembles a self-antigen, which then allows for expansion of the, or activation of the self-reactive lymphocyte.
So, those are two examples of triggers, either bystander activation or molecular mimicry.
The final point that I would like to make here is that it's very important to recognize that triggers are essential.
For example, when patients have genetic susceptibility, for example, let's say that the patients have HLA-B27, that does not mean that the patient is automatically going to develop autoimmunity.
In fact, most patients with HLA-B27 actually never develop autoimmune disorders.
So, again, that just highlights the importance of the role of this trigger.
The final point that I would like to make is that these disorders, i.e. autoimmune disorders, are generally clinically progressive.
Now, what happens is the patients tend to get relapses and remissions.
And the reason they get relapses and remissions is because the antigen is always present.
And so, you get exposure to the antigen.
You get amplification of the immune system.
That results in a flare.
Eventually, the immune response remits.
The patient goes along.
And then, all of a sudden, there's a relapse with a flare with amplification of the immune response.
And so, that's a classic presentation of autoimmune disorders that they relapse and they remit.
And then, finally, the last point that I would like to make is that often there's overlapping features between autoimmune disorders.
Now, we're going to study several autoimmune disorders in a few minutes.
And you're going to see that sometimes the features can overlap.
And the reason that features can overlap is due to something called epitope spreading.
So, imagine that the patient has a self-reactive lymphocyte that is reacting against the self-antigen.
When those self-reactive lymphocytes get activated and expand, they'll destroy the tissue.
And when they destroy the tissue, new antigens that the immune system hasn't normally seen are going to be exposed.
And so, other lymphocytes can begin to react against those new antigens.
And that can result in overlapping features in these disorders.
So, the exposure of new antigens with the subsequent spreading of the immune response to additional antigens is called epitope spreading.
And epitope spreading can be one explanation of why we might see overlapping features in the disorders that we're going to cover.
So, that concludes this theoretical portion of autoimmunity.
The last point that I'd like to make actually concerns here what's on the bottom of the slide.
I think it's pretty obvious if anybody were to read it.
However, we do appreciate your respecting the legal copyright along with the ethical copyright that goes along with the Pathoma materials.
So, again, thank you for making Pathoma one of the most widely used pathology resources throughout the world.